welcome everyone to
voices with raviki i'm joined by my
friend and
my friends and colleagues uh jordan uh
hall
and uh greg enriquez and um i
i'd like each one of them to i'm sure
many of you have
uh seen both of them before because i've
had multiple conversations with both of
them
but i thought i'd give them each a
moment uh to
um introduce themselves what we're going
to do today is we're going to
uh enter into dear logos about trying
to um explicate
and elucidate the connections between
our works various work and see what
emerges from that so
who would like to go first in
introducing themselves
i'll go ahead uh greg enriquez professor
of grad psych
uh graduate psychology at james madison
university and uh
interested in theoretical uh psychology
unifying psychology
so that we can guide our way toward uh
wisdom in the 21st century
nice yeah so before we start the call i
mentioned that this kind of
question is like almost intractable for
me and
one of the things that i noticed is a
very distinct sense of resistance to
trying to create a finite set of
semantics uh particularly anything
attached to this notion of my biography
because
it almost certainly can't be the thing
okay almost like if you were gonna i
could i could
invoke some subset of my biography which
is always going to be a projection right
some slice through the whole thing right
but even that probably isn't relevant
because what i can say for sure is that
i'm definitely part my my thing is i'm
in some kind of journey
into the future right and one of the big
areas of inquiry is what
what is it what is the self that is in
that journey into the future
and what is that aspect of biography
that is not coming along for that
journey
right and i don't have a good answer to
that like i don't know and a big part of
this is a necessity to not know because
otherwise you may be holding on to stuff
that's not supposed to be coming along
um so that's that that inquiry like that
that that continual process of extending
into that journey into the future
and the increasing increasing
capacity i hope to be able to be more
elegant
in that to be more fully capable of
making those choices on a momentary
basis
i would say is the best way of naming
the event that sometimes referred to as
me sweet
that was beautiful very good that's uh
i mean so jordan does what i don't think
what that's what i
thought he would do uh he exemplifies he
doesn't just speak and what
i found you exemplifying there jordan is
one of the primary
i don't know what to call it the
metanoias we're meaning that you know
that changing of no
no noises how you notice but also that
sense of conversion like religious
conversion
um that's at the core of many of the
wisdom traditions you see it in stoicism
very clearly
you see it in taoism very clearly i
think you see it in
these diversions of buddhism with which
i'm familiar which is the
the shifting uh from the function the
shifting of the function of
identification off of horizontal
autobiography
onto what i might call vertical ontology
where you're
you're identifying more with the
ontological functionality
of who you are rather than
the autobiographical functionality of
who you are and i think that is one of
the
primary um components of
wisdom uh precisely because and this i
think is very relevant to
the way you've even situated this
conversation it is one of the primary
ways in which
human beings can respond
profoundly and possibly adequately um
to the perennial problem of their
mortality where mortality doesn't mean
the fact
that we're going to die that's that's
like in
ivan ilich ivan ellis knew he was going
to die the way you know the two plus two
equals four
but mortality in the sense that uh that
was really
championed by the prank the pragmatists
like james and others
right that we are always finite
vulnerable and in transformation
and yet nevertheless that doesn't mean
that we can exist in an are a purely
arbitrary fashion
we have to find a place between
algorithmic certainty
and arbitrary you know an arbitrary
license
and that and get getting to be mortal in
that way requires that shift
and and like i said just before we begin
i knew
jordan would just something in that in
that
in that in that moment and he did you
just exemplified something
that i think is central um to
wisdom practices and i think one of the
things that i think
is coming into articulation in both
senses of the word right now
in the in what we're in you know the
meta crisis the meaning crisis
the complexity acceleration that you
talk about jordan is
both a confrontation with and a need to
reconceptualize
that mortality amen
uh i i i know you were checking out tap
cause to stewart kaufman's uh the
adjacent possible
uh when i was reading his stuff he
talked about the unprestatable future
unprestatable and so how do we
uh connect to the past and this what i
call the sea of effect
that has happened and the sea of
possibility that we
ride the edge of and see and so
and i mean where that comes into what i
just said was exactly
that that's you know to capitalize on
andy clark's
phrase you know that's the wave of
uncertainty
and that's the way we're writing right
now and jordan i've been talking about
that
and so i mean that that's an interesting
thing uh maybe we can explore uh
because here's here's a possibility i'll
throw it out and we'll see if it
germinates
i think it obviously connects directly
immediately to a lot of what jordan's
doing because
i just tried to articulate that and then
brad you and i have had discussions
about spirituality within psychotherapy
in which i think one way we could talk
about
that is exactly this that human beings
have to
confront deeply and come to appreciate
their mortality as something not just in
terms of their autobiography
but you know in terms of like a lot of
the stuff you talk about
absolutely right no i mean it's the um
obviously the existentialist frankel
talks about the will to mean
will to meaning right uh and and
fundamentally how do we align ourselves
across the levels of levels and
dimensions of our existence
on the time continuum that places
ourselves
um in a juxtaposed uh
situation when i was uh when i built the
tree of knowledge for the first 10 years
interesting enough to riff a little bit
more
um the the metaphor what i have and i'll
show you at some point
is ride the wave that's what it was
called uh ride the weight
hot excellent awesome check this out so
you got like um
uncertainty and you got relationship
with uncertainty right and there's
basically two or three basic moves like
one mode is uncertainties out there and
you're like oh uncertainty i'm
going to pull back right
right and in that in that mode one of
them one of the subsidiary responses is
oh i'm going to reduce the uncertainty
right but that's actually coming from
the disposition of pulling back
in the context of uncertainty then
there's this other mode which we might
call adventure
i hope uncertainty is is the necessary
condition for any kind of adventure
so then the next thing is like that i
was feeling the felt sense of being a
polynesian like way back in the day
and like i remember having a
conversation with a new friend of mine
about what was the what was the felt
sense of
being a polynesian getting ready to go
in the ocean the key
insight was this there was this uh we
even talked about it john
faith there was faith and it was faith
in the sense of groundedness right
for sure no idea what lay beyond the
horizon and simultaneously
such a comprehensive connection with the
milieu
so integrated with the ocean in all of
its languages
that there was just a sense of
connection of groundedness
in the uncertainty that it was in fact
continuous adventure like there was an
openness into it
and there's that that that ride the wave
right you actually have to
achieve or accomplish a level of
embodied mastery of being in
relationship with the flow of the
reality that you're in
that allows you to be in relationship
with uncertainty as the unfolding of
infection
bingo so it sounds like the the
the two come together then right so
uh and i think the polynesian metaphor
is wonderful because
uh you know that that move to an
ontological sense of identity and you're
invoking it jordan with the groundedness
it's very participatory yeah it's
participatory and perspectival
um not that the propositional and the
procedural aren't there they
are but there's the groundedness there's
the alignment
and then there's that it's almost like
there's that you know
garfield talks about the felt sense of
consciousness there's a sense of
you know of a trekking right uh you know
that there's a
and plato talks about this you get that
this gets aligned
in such a way that um
there there's that there there's that
trust
that and yeah a synergistic rhythm you
know
yeah rhythm that that that embodies you
as you ride the cusp of the wave as a
especially if we can get it
harmonized across units you then have
the collective
i recommend the boys in the boat if you
want a description of it that's a great
uh narrative of the 1936 crew team
um about how crew how certain crew teams
can get in such a precise rhythm
yeah that they become the whole so
aren't those both like i'm and now i'm
using like stereoscopic vision aren't
those
fused the way the left and right field
are fused into depth perception
when you're doing psychotherapeutic
practice because presumably
i mean you're focused on the client but
you have to be like you have to be
aligned and in tune with yourself
and you have to be riding the wave
because they're a complex system and
they're going to
be unfolding in unpredictable ways and
because there's
you know because there's factors that
are unknown to them unknown to you
that are you know driving everything
that's happening there so
that must be something that's very
pregnant when you're doing
psychotherapy oh absolutely uh you know
i mean i say good psychotherapy always
starts with rogers and roger's
fundamental task
was to essentially empathize with the
core organismic valuing process of the
of the individual's heart okay and so
you then you have to get through the
social self and the
conflicts and the you know that
that is actually the
defense against uncertainty and threat
right that causes them to freeze cause
them get rageful
causes them to flee causes them to be
obsequious uh those are sort of four
poles in sort of uh if you go into
polyvagal theory you could see that
embodiment of defense
okay you have to weave through that
stuff and then
start the process of honing and
mirroring so the person can actually be
like hey wait a minute there is a
potentially a way
to harmonize with something inside of
myself my conscious self and the other
and and see that there's a potential
here for this uncertainty to grow
in a positive direction
okay so one of the things that i've
noticed i've been really curious about
now for the past
say three or four years is is what is
the primary protocol for
relationship in so
we can put this a little bit more
context crew
the notion of crew maps very closely to
the notion of tribe which is to say that
our instinct in the context of crew
is to shrink the number of relationships
to a small number that is cultivated
over some long period of training
together
exactly what i would propose is that
that is going to be an error that we
actually have to learn how to create a
capacity a
a protocol for relationality that
enables us to effectively crew
on a flowing basis to move and
enter like what we're doing right now
the three of us have have a level of
relationship
we are definitely not a crew but if we
can actually achieve this mastery i hate
to use the
learn i should go with hyper instead of
meta if we can look at a hyper crew
we can effectively find a way to
establish that protocol what you just
said i think is super powerful it's
almost like
you know how in the process of um of
development we recapitulate the entire
history of evolution from
you know biology all the way up right
you're saying is look when i first meet
somebody we're going to have to
recognize we have to start with zero so
we're going to engage in a
mammal to mammal interaction it's not
listen we're not we haven't begun the
process of
of of communication at the level of
neocortex
first thing we're going to have to do is
just have a primary protocol which is
allowing our bodies to come into a felt
sense of oh
okay there's a there's a safeness and a
non-defensiveness in this space that we
can actually begin to communicate
then it begins to build that's right
it's called attachment security because
attachment obviously when you were born
it's to what extent does that relational
system start harmonizing or not
and become secure insecure with the
dance of the
usually mother but whoever the primary
caretaker and then secondary caretakers
are
that lays down the phylogenetic to
ontogenetic
primate core and then you have to figure
out how to dance with that and what it's
tracking at its intuition
is what's called relational value that's
am i known and valued here at my core
or i have to fake it do i have to hide
it what the hell am i
okay and so then you if you mirror with
them and you track and then they're
intuiting
hey is this guy trust me is he real of
interest is he just going through a
protocol
you know it's just sort of checking
boxes so he covers his ass i mean these
are all the
subtle tests uh that are happening when
somebody say comes into the office
and and is looking for something they
don't even know what they're looking for
so i'm wondering then if that if this
it sounds like this plugs into something
uh
that you and i uh greg have been talking
about which is
and then jordan you and i and chris and
i have been trying to work out
is the problem
and uh what's the guy who wrote
philosophical companionship talks about
this
the problem with um uh therapy
is is it is focused on a particular
individual
right and and that and of course we need
therapy so this is in no way a criticism
of therapy
but what we've talked about greg is the
idea about
can we find a way to exact the skill set
uh um from things like psychotherapy
out into an existential arena
completely i i'm actually i'm seriously
considering
uh you know whether i'm going to retain
my license okay i'm going through a bit
of a professional crisis
okay because um as my vision of what the
world needs is
what needs to happen i went from oh my
god look at all these beautiful
psycho technologies right right and then
they're beautiful psycho technologies
that are now cloistered in professional
offices
okay right and then behind the scenes
and then
and then i'm at the systemic level i've
started wonder more and more over the
last 10 years like so what does it mean
you have your shitty relationships out
here and i don't you know whatever
right and then you go in and we create
this cultivated perfect cloistered
relationship where i mirror you as a
professional
right and then you get this sort of
known felt of existence then you go back
out into the real world
all right and especially it's not
uncommon then all of a sudden actually
say wait a minute
you're my best person who i want to talk
to you're the person i want to connect
to
because actually you mirror me and this
whole thing is actually gratifying my
core
needs in a particular way well uh hello
this is not what it should be if this is
the core of relation
why isn't that distributed across
families and communities
across companies or wherever why why are
we actually
so actually i've been very i've had a
shift in terms of my own
framing about what and of course we need
psychotherapy um but i
am not certain that it doesn't actually
start to create a negative externality
in the way in which we start to think
about relationships and other kinds of
issues
and these are things that i have to
distribute into uh
into what i would call the metaculture
or you know the culture into
this is the uh this is the relationships
for the civilian you know i mean yeah
yeah
so this i think there's a formal way of
actually describing this domain um it's
called the commons
and so the recognition say look guys
there's actually three fundamental
domains and we've eliminated one of them
and we've been trying to navigate
reality with just two
um you've got the the formal domain of
of the state
informal relationships organized
according to some kind of objective
sense you've got the formal domain of
the market
you know the relationship of therapists
you've got the commons right which is
actually more fundamental it is the
basis of the other two
what we've done is we've actually
eliminated the commons almost entirely
and moved into one of those two
categories
and what you're pointing out is that
hell like this concept of the
therapist is actually just called friend
in in in the simplest version right and
by the way parent is the subsidiary of
friend right it's just a different yeah
if we go to
aristotle's version of what friendship
is absolutely worse that's what we
should be
exactly right so returning that finding
a way and by the way i think that's also
the answer to the point of the meeting
crisis
like the meaning crisis is nothing more
or less
than that i think that's right and that
that just drives what i'm going to say
next because
the place in which we try to practice
the commons and i'm going to introduce
another term
um because i think friendship uh i think
we've lost the aristocrine sense too
much
so i'm going to use a term that's
somewhat archaic um but
it's good fellowship we used to have a
capacity for
fellowship with people and the place
where we practice fellowship and this
comes from my own
thinking was in was in a religious
context one of the things that religion
did
was what do we hold in common what do we
what do we
right um and then of course the very
problem that we're talking about
it arises as a tension within religion
and it's it's basically a prototypical
instance is the teravadin
mahayana split right well no the way you
do this is you actually retreat into a
monastery
where it's cloistered if you use your
term greg no mahayana says no no
we we don't we need it so that everybody
can be
right everybody can get access to
we need yes we can have people in the
monastery
but we need we need that that's not
where that's not where it's at
that what that does is that's basically
let's treat that like a lab
where we'll test out stuff and one of
the primary design features of that lab
is it has to be to use paul van der
kley's phrase it has to be scalable
it has to be scalable okay and if not
then
it's not actually we shouldn't be
supporting that monastery anymore
sorry so i propose to you that yes i
think it lines up with the meeting
crisis because as we've lost
religion and as we've lost the
relationship between the monastery
and the school the university we've lost
fellowship and we've lost the lab for uh
improving it and we've lost though that
the way in which that's supposed to then
feedback
into the comments brilliant brilliant
and that goes right with black science
notion right of course that at a
foundational level what we're trying to
do here
is create the proper education in this
time between worlds and we have to tr
re-translate right and the other word
that came to mind in terms of
cultivating the commons in the religious
context or in the in our west
is agape right it's like how do we hold
and for me relational value is the term
that i use is being known and valued by
important others and and really it's if
we're going to network the commons
together
um in a healthy way it is fostering
mutual relational value
well i think that picks up on tulip's
definition of agape right
agape is the creative love that creates
persons within
a community of person and that's exactly
the so we've lost we've lost the notion
i think i think and these two get lost
together i would argue
um we've lost the notion of personhood
and we and we've noticed we started with
that because that's what jordan was
exemplifying a different notion of
personhood
remember or a vertical we've lost these
two notions in a correlated fashion
we've lost the notion of personhood as
something that we all
have to do together adoptically and
therefore we've lost also the
corresponding notion of fellowship
right so our culture we have been
reduced to citizens of the state
and consumers of the market we are not
participant persons
within the culture anymore right that's
great because the tree of knowledge what
it
what it identifies then matter life mind
culture
and then it identifies well what are the
nodes of operation in each and so
basically an atom a cell an animal and a
person okay so the culture person and
that's our self-conscious justification
in a noted network of justification
systems that embodied in a set of
practices
okay so the fundamental thing is
actually how do we network the culture
together
we regulate it off to the goddamn state
right and
then mechanically oriented economically
and then we we got it uh religiously
boom the commons is is becomes shallow
empty and broken
so that means we've sort of articulated
two problems then
one one way and you can see it in
directions
one is uh how do we and i'm using this
word
very deliberately how do we exact what
we've learned
from psychotherapy and how do we
exact what we can remember from our
religious history
such that we can get what is needed now
to get back what jordan is calling
the comments and i've tried to give a
little bit of grammar to that notion
as the place in which you know
personhood
and fellowship are being are the central
things being cultivated
my mind was turning to history
to the actual the actual specific
history that gave rise to where we are
okay how did this thing come to pass and
then what does that tell us about
how we might then proceed into the
future excellent and i was also
integrating in
um the the exterior we might call it the
socio-technical or the
objective sociological mode right so
which i'm doing the interior
psychological
and it's we could do the same thing and
i think it's important to actually do it
so
you know if you're looking at um many of
the biggest problems that we are facing
today at the level of the objective
has to do with the fact that we're
trying to solve commons problems
using markets and states yes well
certainly
really excellent that's a very yeah
start that thing yeah put a pin in that
just say that again double click that
that is really good that is really good
and i should uh mention by the way um
i i'll actually want to i may have to
actually literally take off and search
for it because i
had a conversation maybe a week ago with
a woman in australia who is like going
to be my primary mentor in this because
this has been her life's work is exactly
this question
and of course there's michelle ballins
and the pdp people who've been working
on the commons question for quite some
time so there's a whole crew here
right right right just kind of reference
that crew
in a big way but um yeah so
it's funny i i imagine i'm almost sure
that if we actually spent the time to
look at it historically there is a like
a one-for-one correlation you guys know
about the the enclosure movement in
england
no i don't all right so i know vaguely
about it yeah
in the transition of the time period the
the john you talk about in the meeting
crisis of that 15 to 1600s
where a lot of stuff was going on in
terms of mind
at exactly that moment of course
capitalism was showing up right
and one of the like first moves in
capitalism is they had to engage in
enclosure they had to move
property land out of the commons that
was being managed by
a medieval commoning institutional
structure
into private ownership which could then
be made available
into the into the into the institutions
of capitalism as it was beginning to
evolve
right right right so you know that move
happened or that's that's
we have a nice historical track of that
and played a huge role particularly
because it was england it was the place
where it first happened because the
english like
pop this is what we have to do so
there's like a rendering available to an
institutional structure that had certain
kinds of um
i would imagine probably locally optimal
capacities right
rarely are these things entirely
malevolent they're usually just
short-sighted
um and there's a double coordination
like we can let's just kind of do the
historical moment right
my wife and i were talking about
education and i said look let's put that
into historical context
you have the movement of the mass
movement of population
in the period of the 1800s from the farm
into the city and in particular from the
farm into the factory
and contaminants with that in the latter
part of it you also had this notion of
wait a minute
eight-year-olds working in factories is
a bad idea
oh but wait we can we will we want the
parents to still be working in factories
so now we have to actually have a place
to put the kids right so this is
the beginning of the notion of
educational institutions as daycare was
actually
a secondary effect of the
the emergence of the idea we should
teach not put kids in factories
but no solution to the problem how do we
deal with the fact that we still want to
put their parents in factories
okay we'll put them in schools right so
you actually glom daycare on to
education and uh set up like factories
too
and and right we have this the arc that
tyson young
brought to my attention most notably in
his book about the
the specific prussian model of of
education right there's lots of
different models of education lived in
western civilization
the prussians who are a very unique
character in this story right
who just happened to have beat the crap
out of the austrians right the austrian
astropressure war and then the frankfurt
pressure yeah yeah
they they beat the the the habsburg
monarchs right
then they beat the french like back to
back okay there's like the two big guys
in the continent with the austrians and
the pr
and the french and so the prussians just
show up as being like the holy
who the are those guys they came
out of nowhere they just won the
champion back to back
so everybody's like oh we gotta cop with
the prussians william james actually
talks about this problem uh in in in
this conversation the continental
um germanic philosophy was certainly
rising up as being the big thing because
the prussians were winning
pretty well right that's right the
prussians the persians had formally and
intentionally
adopted a hyper control structure in the
way they did education
they they were the model of we want to
create
highly regular highly controllable um
entire populace the way this thing works
is everything has to be a rigorously
controlled hierarchy
and everybody is a highly trained
soldier effectively
and and soldier in the narrow sense like
not warrior soldier like frederick the
great's
clockwork army like playing a cog in the
bigger machine
and the thing is that particular
approach this is the reciprocal closing
piece that moves
john you know i've talked about where
there's like why do people get into
reciprocal closing well the answer is
because
it works in the first couple of moves i
get this ability to extract
energy in the short term which gives me
a local advantage i can create this war
machine i create the society which is
hyper coordinated around
controllable structures actually maps to
this notion of uncertainty and control
it's
coming from the same psychology right in
fact i have to protect myself i can
actually create a defense mechanism that
kind of
works in the immediate term the problem
is everybody else in western
civilization got infected by it
particularly in the us like at exactly
the moment when the us was becoming a
state
it could be coordinated across that
territory and and and the problem of
industrialization was beginning to
raise a bigger problem okay what do we
do with all these kids and they'll say
we're now going to create adopt emulate
the germanic model
of formal education and boom america has
that structure right
and so so let's move this up to the top
remember the meta piece here is this
forcing everything out of the commons
out of the family out of real
relationality
out of people deliberating on things in
some different model
into one of these two modes right the
market and the state right
and we can kind of track i don't know if
it's useful we can certainly do the
product do the process
of tracking any given element of the
interior and the exterior over the past
250 years or so of that movement
and that will then let us tell us a lot
about where we are now we can see how we
got here and you'll tell us a lot about
where we are now
right and then the next question of
course is where do we go right
right well that reminds me you know i
work a bit with
lenny rachel anderson her work on
metamodernity
okay emphasizes the nordic secret um
which was the educational structures
that the nordic countries started to
know which was basically character
development
okay so they shifted and they basically
took personal
and communitized kind of development
emphases
and that took them from a really
difficult condition
uh over a hundred years to a flourishing
uh society at least relatively speaking
yeah
so the philosophy of education that bill
dong
that's a term for it that emphasizes a
bit more personal development a bit more
character
uh a bit more community um and commons
would have that commons flavor
um so that is part of to me then the
ideas about what
what kind of educational process and
what kind of orientation
is appropriate you know for us in the
current age
uh given the completely new landscape of
problems and possibilities
that we are facing so yeah i'm familiar
with that argument too greg
thomas bjorkman makes that argument yep
i mean they make it together you know
they're they're co-authors so so
that it's interesting to try and sort of
pair so
like when the enclosure movement is
happening you get the rise of
la right and then you're going to get
and you've got the english symbol
you get the rise of individualism which
really goes well
uh with both uh in the enclosure
movement and with kind of the
automatization of the individual that
capitalism
uh really really uh works with so and
then when you get
depression and frederick degrade who's
his
philosopher it's kant and with font
you get right the uh you get
the reduction this is a little over
simplistic but at least
this is at least how the popular version
of conte if i can put it that way
you get the reduction of religion to
piety and to duty
and where duty and piety are ways of
understanding religion that are now
removed from
participation in the comments you lose
you in fact you're suspicious of what
what layman pascal calls the overflow
that is actually one of the defining
features
like and when we talk about it here when
we talk about dialogues we get the
overflow when we come into a comment
like you know the the proper locus of
distributed cognition is the commons
and what the state and the market do is
they keep trying to say no no
we are the proper place in which
distributed cognition functions
and what we keep and you know and this
was kafka's great
understanding right is you know the the
the manifest and the latent functions
come apart
repeatedly weber's idea right favor is
also part of this whole
right vapor vapor is the first one of
the first
sociological to use your where you put
us jordan
you know critical responses to the
prussian state right
you know the protestant work ethic and
the whole idea that
what you have right is if you if you do
this homogenization if you get
right and you've got what he when he he
lumped the two together
in terms of this process he called
bureaucratization that everything is
everything is becoming bureaucratic and
he said exactly what jordan said
you get the intoxicating salience of the
manifest function that says
look at how rapidly we can get things in
order and get things running
but what you have is the latent function
the latent functionality is
right all that calming stuff all that
persons
and community stuff doesn't go away but
what it does is it gets subverted and
undermined
so a concrete example is the bureaucracy
has the manifest function
right of making everything ordered but
it has the latent
function of diffusing responsibility and
shifting blame
so that people cease to be listen please
they cease to be persons within
community and
kafka gets that and he holds it up in
art and he says
luck luck look he keeps doing that again
and again and again and this like we
could loop back to the conversation
about therapy like that's
that's the experience right that
experience of this
is industrial model right i'm taking
things what is it foucault right the
disciplinary society
yeah i've got this bizarre thing that
the thing that is the most fundamentally
human
which is real authentic relationship has
been fact commoditized by turned into a
product
put it into a formal relationship which
bizarrely enough
i can imagine this sort of thing like
you know oh our arrow's up we're not
even i don't even know you anymore stop
talking
immediately well the boundaries of the
professional relation and the
termination when it's over and
i mean you know which is just like like
walking off the factory floor like
you've just
left the factory floor i don't care
anymore i'm not canning you know soup
anymore i'm now like coming over this
place like
discontinuous transitions and now you
know as i move away from it
you see the weird alienating aspect of
i'm going to professionalize this very
intimate personal relationship
right and we're going to we're going to
have to navigate the codes of my
profession and then intersect them in
the genuine relationship i
taught this all the time about how to
navigate it but i was inside of it now
much more outside was like you know
we gotta
undo that at somehow and reverse it to
get it into the commons to use the
brilliant word you know that really
describes what it is that i was supposed
to so
i mean i've been trying with all with
your
help from both of you guys collaboration
and other things
you know i've been trying to you know
work out this notion
because there's a there's this whole
family and it should be a family i'm not
trying to be reductive
but this family of practices um like
that engender deal logos and i'm trying
to bring back the psychotech
of you know dialectic and you know their
circling and authentic relating and
insight dialogue and philosophy
the list of these is just pervasive
right
but they and and again i think that
plurality is a good thing
i think they and i i mean this very
seriously i'm playing with
thickenslang's notion but i'm i'm double
playing on it right
there's a family there's a family
resemblance and a family relationship
between all of these uh modalities and
trying to get them
trying to figure out like how to do what
i keep circling back on what you just
put your finger on right how do we
how do we transpose from the second what
we've learned from psychotherapy but
also how do we transpose
what we learned from the ancient
philosophical practices around wisdom
like where like the philia the
fellowship around wisdom was how you
coordinated
uh distributed cognition for persons
within a community of person how do we
get
like i'm trying to draw on those and say
what can we how can we get um
you know a family resemblance family
relationship
set of practices that will give
people back well i think what we're
talking about here
but i i come to a deep recognition
and appreciation of i think jordan's
point that
all of that if you'll allow me a
somewhat obsolete
metaphor now if all of that software
work that i've been talking about
uh depends on a significant hardware
change that jordan is trying to talk
about with
with the civilian project that i mean
there's enough
truth in marx that if you don't change
also
you know you know the socioeconomic
habitats of people
you can only get so far right i was i've
been impressed by how
all of these traditions like the
epicureans
retreat to the garden the stoics have
the porch
right and the plateness have the academy
which is the grove
like what they do is they try to
re-situate human beings
into environmental cultural
environmental contexts that
are conducive uh to our you know
our evolutionary history the fact that
we're primarily hunter-gatherers
right that do that but nevertheless try
to put on top of it
this this project that we're talking
about um so
i think that uh i mean i i
i think well i i'm trying to i guess a
book from jordan
the the the how everything we're talking
about here
has to be has to be coordinated
and again i'm doing this with the hands
because i don't know what this looks
like
but the software and the hardware have
to be coordinated so they're mutually
affording in some way
yeah well there's a lot here agreed
completely
like super profoundly completely i think
of it actually is in some sense more of
an opportunity than a challenge
because what it does is it allows you to
like if you run into a problem it feels
very intractable in the domain of say
psychology
um heuristic switch to the objective
domain and perhaps you actually if you
if you make a shift over there it
actually completely prunes a whole bunch
of problems that you're facing in in the
psychological domain and maybe vice
versa there's actually a way of getting
synergy value from that
uh the woman's name from australia by
the way is kylie kylie stegman
oh thank you i've only just begun to
have conversations with her but
her focus as far as i can tell is
actually on the question of the object
like how do we do things like
rainforests and uh
um the atmosphere that said
i haven't spent enough time so she may
actually have a lot of insight into the
into the subject of
the interest objective as well um
oh crap oh okay so one of the things
that i saw as you were talking john
was i was remembering the common
commentation about the notion that
there's a right relationship between the
monastery and
the community yeah right and and i think
there's actually two roles there maybe
one that was kind of been
a little bit a little bit more secret
which is the relationship between the uh
the appendix and the and the gut biome
right
brett weinstein points this out he's
like hey guys the appendix isn't
actually not
it's not uh obsolete what's the word
vestigial it's not vestigial
it's a it's a it's a place that holds is
so fully disconnected from the gut
that the gut biome can be highly
destroyed by lots of different
environmental factors and yet a
microcosm
of a full gut violence stored in the
appendix
and so what happens is it's basically a
source of regrowth so there's like
the monastery actually plays two roles
on the one place
it's cloistering enables it to survive
and hold
to some level the seed corn the seed
bank
culture codes and also innovate on them
so that as the larger culture like
becomes
uh the ecosystem begins to
degrade there's a way to actually go
back into the monastery and say geez we
need to bring come back out of the
monastery
we shouldn't have done that appendectomy
we should have let that thing there so
we can recalibrate we can recalibrate
yeah that's awesome so there's something
there too because there's something yeah
the reactivation of the monastery and
the opening of the gates
and the returning of the monks back into
community to
to bring these culture codes back into
community
but the problem you're naming is you
know that is it man and i think that
aligns greg also with the conversations
we've been having around the notion of
what's this transformational threshold
which is just basically the last move of
culture space
exactly right so so right so
if we now situate ourselves in the
landscape afforded by the tree of
knowledge
you then sit yourself so culture has
evolved into a particular point the
culture-person plane
this is the behavior of persons mediated
by systems of justification that then
legitimize
informational control both of our
actions and of the material environment
situated in a
um on the ecology of the earth okay
and but what the material culture
was different okay separate a tool
although an extension of mind
is not feeding back on our systems of
justification in a particular way
that changes when we start writing so
the first techno that really starts to
fundamentally change the way we justify
in terms of because it creates this
external memory okay
and then the civilizations you know in
writing and then all that stuff starts
to get networked together in this
industrial code
and the modernist industrial code then
we're talking about the ways in which
now is trying to regulate the behaviors
and create institutional codes
that actually are alienating it for us
from the commons okay
but from the particular angle that the
tree of knowledge affords is you're
saying
pay attention to the information
processing within systems and
communication between systems
because those are the planes of
existence that then result in
potentially qualitative shifts
okay check this out man all right
so
the metaphor that i use a lot that
really helps me is the movement from
complex chemistry into neurons right
the point of that movement is that
neurons have a very high degree of
fidelity and precision right given
an input the output is always the same
and lots of noise gets filtered out okay
now
transpose that into the level of culture
right every move
at the level of interpersonal
relationship that shows up as
noise is the thing that actually has to
be eliminated from our relationships
so particularly every move that is
intentional noise i.e
being a dick like in all the different
forms right right the problem of
and manipulation
right one level right and whether and
there's
no sorry well there it is here we go
we're back in community
we're back in the conference yes that's
the way it should be right it's funny
our lack of haircuts and our lack of
formal clothes is actually a really
powerful reminder
of the force returned to the comments i
will go ahead and shift this to keep the
jive here
but yeah go ahead um
yeah so the move that move at the end of
culture space at least one
fundamental like probably a third is
precisely
the mastery at all nodes of
techniques of a showing up authentically
and b noticing when noise is being
injected
into the relationship and rapidly
exiting that out of the relationship
right
absolutely this is that's great so this
is certain terms of the own
psychotechnologies that are embedded in
this unified theory of knowledge that i
built
okay um is how do you track what's
called the gi
dynamics i just this is in the chapter i
did for uh
john's book gi dynamics refer to the
justification
okay so this is the frame of our
language systems our investments what is
the vector of our the direction of our
intention
okay and the influence which is how are
we bouncing off of other people
and our gi dynamics in harmony or not
okay
so when we're jiving gi dynamics are in
harmony we have shared justification
we have shared intentionality our
investment systems are intertwined
then boom something happens you get
kicked out okay
or you realize somebody's got different
divergent paths somebody's going to get
hurt
then you drop into your defense now
you're going to protect yourself you're
going to justify defensively you're
going to move
you're either going to get fearful
aggressive etc okay
so that's now all of a sudden you get
bumped and now all of a sudden there's a
totally different harmony this happens
all the time right
you know all of a sudden somebody makes
an accusation somebody slips up somebody
does certain things now you're
here okay so now that when that happens
that's the defensive
place where and defense starts
to occur
right then everybody's going to try to
return to equilibrium
i'm going to try to get my justified
state of blame so my relational value is
secure
so i'm a good person and you can't put
me on trial and accuse me and cost me
that's where people go and so then you
pull in your defense attorney lawyer
press secretary and you start
the process
of hey i'm going to do this okay now
active manipulators
do this systematically right they're
trying to then gain social influence
they don't give a about relational
value but they're actually going to
manipulate the structure
so the outside consequences they get
more influence in the end
all right so both of those are very very
dangerous all right
so you have to commit to a value
structure for me be that which enhances
dignity
and well-being with integrity those are
my big three meta values
which which orient then the
transcendence again say this again
dignity okay so this is a fundamental
respect and it actually goes to an
ultimate aesthetic value uh and
realistically is the value of value in
humans
okay each person has dignity it also
justifies human rights in the universal
declaration of human rights
okay well-being is happiness with the
worthiness to be happy to quote
kant okay and it refers to the
fundamental orientation of your
subjective
your health and functioning in the
environment to foster potential growth
okay and then integrity is honesty honor
and soundness
all right so those are the and they
often they content there's tensions
between those
all right so i try to align my being
with those big three
that's what and that's what i i invite
everybody when i
when i think about you know what's a
person a good faith okay
it's somebody that has some form of
universal value structure
that is committed to them above their
ego right
it's a love or or some sort of some sort
of notion
some ultimate concern that says hey it's
more important than me
and i'm going to orient myself to that
so what you're talking about
is if i understand this you're talking
about
to circle back a bit you're talking
about a normativity on the vertical
dimension
exactly we're talking about a
normativity by which people can
uh understand um
and get in get into right relationships
all of these different levels of who and
what they are
exactly let's see oriented towards the
ultimate concern or transcendent
you know you know right it's it's the
ultimate uh end
for an aristotle aristotelian
perspective right it's sort of what is
what is it there that is good uh that
transcends
infinity i mean you know that is that is
the orienting point
okay so then yeah go i was just going to
say
uh that that affords a question now
comes to my mind then
i think we're on the edge of
articulating a question at least i find
it
an important question to ask because it
has both theoretical and practical input
how do i distinguish the
manipulators
from the people how do i distinguish uh
how do i distinguish
from emerging beauty right
we're talking about justification
systems right the thing about that
look the noise is not an intrinsic
feature
right noise is relative to what you find
relevant right signal noise differences
and so if i like if i'm in this
justification system
then xyz are going to count as noise but
if i move to this justification system
xyz now may be central this is the whole
cuny and the anomalies become the center
of the new paradigm
right you and i were talking about
something like this yesterday so
how do i distinguish people
who are not playing the game fairly
because they're manipulators
from people who say no no i want to i
want to play an infinite game here
rather than a finite game and i want i
want to get i i
right yeah right
we're with you yeah right there's not
first off we know that there can't be a
simplistic
complicated code for this because as
soon as somebody has a simplistic
complicated code they'll just use it and
you right
so it is that you have to be in a
participatory jazz rift
regulatory structure to see them in
context feel where their motive is
um but they from my vantage point they
should be committed
to some sort of metacultural value
structure in other words there has to be
some notion about what good
is okay and then i have an integrated
pluralistic frame for that so i want to
know what is your ultimate concern your
ultimate purpose
right so that's and at some level then
by i didn't
finish the thought in terms of for
people of good faith the whole commemo
the little black dot
repre on the tree back there represents
what's called comm mo
and that is for individuals of good
faith you jump into a metacognitive
observer's stance so we step outside
say wait a minute what the hell just
happened if somebody get defensive and
based on ego concerns
okay then if so that's okay we get
curious accepting
loving and motivated toward valued
states of being to get back on
a healthy gi dynamic track okay so
it's a psycho technology that says well
wait a minute if we start to get bumped
because we don't get each other and then
we start bullshitting because we see the
other as threat
okay if we are people of good will we
should be able to step outside of that
apply the principles of curiosity
acceptance loving compassion and
motivated toward valued states of being
and then re-establish at least where the
hell we are in relation
let me throw in i think i think i can
handle i think let me just throw in the
pieces coming up for me
okay and i think i thought if i frame it
in the context of parenting i think it
actually gets a lot easier
okay um because what i'm talking about
basically is boundaries
so this is the uh the inverse side right
of at least with what uh greg's bringing
up
um so i'm going to measure it in terms
of my capacity
and by my i mean whatever the we is
right our our interest objective
capacity
to hold the other right
okay now if the other is a
hyper-sophisticated sociopath
i'm just going to define it as my
capacity to hold the other is inadequate
that's it my ability to be in right
relationship with you just is enough
isn't going to work
i cannot find a way to get around that
now you're still asking the question how
do i
what's the signal that lets me know that
that's what's really happening but i'm
gonna
step it back for a second before we get
there because the higher issue is okay
there will definitely be circumstances
in the immediate term
all over the place and in the long term
still irreducibly probably for
a very long period of time maybe forever
where our collective capacity to hold
the other is inadequate to maintain the
relationality
yes therefore we then need to have me
have boundaries right boundaries that
emerge in that environment and hold
the relationship at a level that it can
be held appropriate exactly
um okay that's that and which by the way
this actually shows up as like the
nordic version of
jail it's like look you know you've got
this bad habit you tend to kill people
willy-nilly
we have not yet figured out how to move
you out of that bad habit so we're going
to move you into a context where
the right relationship can be held and
that's actually called a place that has
walls that you can't get out of it
yep right but there's a very different
vibe there right it's
the vibe is very much one of this is on
a continuity of relationship and it
entirely has to do with the
this we're both we're both part part of
this game right yep i can't hold you
you can't hold me there's something
going on here and it's a weed it's the
problem we're just trying to figure out
how to get into a place where the
relationality has
can actually have continuity completely
i've got a whole system of
dimensions called the 5c dimensions
which layers where you are
in intimacy all the way from ultimate
connection which means you're fused
all the way down into conflicted and
controlling which means you're literally
in conflict trying to control the other
person so there's a whole dimension so
the next thing i'm going to bring in
is crude right and i don't like its
crudity but there's something also
i think probably fundamental so perhaps
throwing it out there
which is and sometimes going back to
this notion of like the protocol is
built as a layer of stacks
and so so my short answer to your
question is i know
i know like i'm an interaction with an
experience if i just listen to the way
my body is responding to the experience
if i just listen very closely i know i
know whether i'm about to experience
something of tremendous joy and beauty
there's actually struggle going on the
noise is noise in the context of a
shared intent
or a transcendent effort to create
and when the noise is actually having to
do with something along the lines of
deep levels of manipulation um but
i can't say that my knowing is super
high fidelity
right i can't actually guarantee that i
know for sure and i definitely don't
have a level of skillfulness in my
knowing my sense my sense to be able to
articulate and express it
well clearly and i definitely definitely
don't have a skillfulness of
relationality to manifest that in a
context that can actually bring it into
the right place right
but there's something about that stack
right the reality of going back to our
evolutionary history and saying look
something about the you know mammalian
like uh or the social animal aspect like
some somewhere in that stack there was a
huge effort to figure out how to
actually have extremely high fidelity
sensitivity to this particular move
and you're making a move in that domain
and you know the space between my belly
button my scrotum is right now telling
me that there's something off in the
relationship yep we're gonna have to
slow the down i don't know what's
going on
like that's that's maybe part of the
answer well right and actually what
go ahead yeah this is all good guys
um but
there's a okay and then i i want to
respond
i'm sorry i want to resonate with you
what both of you just said there's
something in both of it
but let me put what i i think
there's one tail end of the curve that
you were talking about but i was
actually more
i was concentrating on the other end um
what i meant by this is
uh let me try it like this um let's say
we do have i'll pick up on both what you
said greg and what you said but
that we have like we have sort of
ultimate concerns in terms of personhood
and what it is to be a person and a
human being right and and all of the
values that you articulated
great they're they're sort of
transcendental in a contin sense
they're constitutive they're they're
necessary they're right conditions for
first
for for personhood flourishing i get
that right
and then and then jordan says and we
have this we have this
instinctive machinery when the stock is
in place
because we we've co-evolved with con
specifics
across so many species that we there's
there's a lot there
however let me still problematize this
because i think we're on
want to something here right right i'm
just i'm trying to be a good soccer
right but here's the thing
all of that machinery is based on
either instinctive or enculturated
notions of what a person is and what
some of the great
people did is they
and this is what nietzsche was trying to
get up with trans valuation they
altered the notion of what a human
person is
so if if i save you no no i'm ultimately
committed to xyz value
what i'm doing is it's locked into a
particular conception
of human personhood and what i'm
suggesting to you and this goes back to
jordan's very first move in this
dialogue is what is in transition now is
exactly that fact
that's what it is be a person i'm not
saying
please i'm not saying we ignore all of
our rich history
all of the philosophy all of the
religion i was psychology i'm not saying
that
but i'm i'm also what i'm saying is we
can't just
let that go forward in an inertial
fashion i think what is in question
right now and therefore and therefore it
puts into question all of those values
which is not the same thing as saying i
reject those values but it puts into
quite what does dignity mean
when my fund like what jesus of nazareth
does is change
what it means to be a person so that
some of the older
notions right are fundamentally
transformed and there's huge resistance
to this
because the people the context of the
time say you're violating the law
the law is what protects our humanity
and then but jesus and saint paul says
no no but
i'm trying to change your notion of what
a human being is
that's you know you know human beings
aren't made for the sabbath the sabbath
is made for human beings right
he's trying to change what it means to
be a human being to be a person
and that means new virtues and new
values like the greeks don't have
faith hope and love they have justice
right and swap for son and wisdom and
courage
we don't throw those out but the
christians give us new ones you see the
problem i'm trying to articulate oh yeah
so how do i distinguish somebody who's
trying to launch us into what i think
need right now which is trans valuation
if they'll allow me the nietzschean term
from somebody who's doing what greg is
mentioning
the person who's manipulating now i
agree jordan that it
whatever we're proposing it's got to
plug into that evolutionary machinery
but if oh
it has to be educated it has to be
educated in some way
all right so yeah i know that we
actually have a bunch of uh
i don't mean this in anything but
actually uh fellowship and love we have
a bunch of christian lurkers that will
sometimes comment on our conversations
yeah and i just heard the voice in my
head what you're asking is how do you
distinguish between christ and
antichrist yes
yes yes the antichrist is defined i
believe as
perfectly simulating right it'll
actually be more salient
the antichrist shows up as the super
salient christ right
so everything that you would use to try
to discern christ hood the antichrist
will show up as being even more so
right yes so it's a hyper problem like
it's the problem you're stating it's
mostly transparent yeah does that
resonate with you john yeah yes it does
and then you can pick up on the
christian medical what christ does i
mean this is
rene gerard's notion right christ right
is within a particular
justification framework right and then
he dies
he dies within it and he breaks and
that's the way in which he tries to
break us
out of a whole way in which we try to
manage
the ultimate concerns around personhood
and gets us the
socrates does the same thing he tries to
reorient how we care
all of these individuals if you'll allow
me a
a happy metaphor they open up the field
of human
personhood of human and correspondingly
human experience
and i think that is what we need right
now and so
again yeah how do we distinguish between
the curse is here too right curse is
right on this right you're asking the
same question how you distinguish
between the
the person who's truly playing the
infinite game yes and then the person
who looks like they might be playing the
infinite game that's actually doing a
really sneaky finite game
yeah and that is very very important
right now i put to you that's what i'm
proposing to you guys
that that is kind of one of the central
problems we're facing because of the way
the cyber technology can super inflate
it can give such a simulcam
of somebody playing the infinite game
because there's all this
complexity and there's all this
information flowing
and there's all of these diverse models
that can be played with
but that person is still ultimately
right ultimately
just being the antichrist well so some
interesting things
this is almost i'm almost like a random
walk space but check this out
okay um so the infinite game has
continuity
yes it's almost the definition of
continuity is the infinite game
the finite game is always has
discontinuity it's like a digital matrix
layered on top of the fundamentally
transcendent if you can engage in a
stochastic hop from model to model this
actually by the way throws off
sociopaths like crazy um
the lack of continuity will show up does
that make sense what i'm saying yep
absolutely you can decode it yeah it
plugs into what you and i were saying
jordan about
the new this new notion of faith as
continuity of contact
right yes spontaneity of contact with
the continuum of reality
yes yes so by the way this is part of
the secret of what i do
is exactly that like the inside of being
of doing
paradigm and domain switching on a
stochastic basis to maintain
to filter out those who are trying to
actually parse things through
a semantic cognitive fine game
methodology and only hang on those who
are actually operating from
seoul okay yeah so this is okay so for
me this is quadrant quadratic coherence
okay so quadrants refer to the willberry
in perspective
can i spell coherence with the q now so
i've got the three cues
do it man absolutely coherent
how's that all right so so now but then
the issue right is the coherence and
integrity of the system obviously this
says this so
crucial to human consciousness is how
much you filter in between the private
and the public
all right you have to then organize and
if your motive structure is actually to
deceive in relation
at some level there's a there is a
disconnect in the frequency
of behavior across the different levels
and and dimensions
and seeking that epistemological
ontological coherence across time
and and that to me that would be an
indicator of
chris a very strong powerful check
indicator yeah
what i'd be looking for and by the way
in a context where the underlying
context of reality is shifting very
rapidly this is john our conversation
the other day about
the end of paradigmatic mind if the
context of reality is shifting within
the
within the time frame where you can
actually re-sync your lack of
fundamental integrity
then you're going to start freaking the
out right right because then you
get disco
you get the coherence yeah because you
try to harmonize it because it's already
you're trying to force the issue
so keep key message here by the way for
those who are interested in the next
move
if you want to endure the transition
under which we are going
dispense with in lack of integrity in
self
because part of the reason why you're
freaking out is you can no longer
maintain your lack of integrity
if you respond and reduce back to
fundamental integrity
then the complexity or the chaos of
reality
no longer will hit against that surface
they can't hold
and by the way that's also the step of
returning to the groundedness of
meaningfulness
the return into fellowship which by the
way also
shows up as the return into the commons
so those are these are all happening
simultaneously
right so yeah you're getting sort of a
very complex
multi-level uh reciprocal opening going
on
kind of thing is that my understanding
absolutely across levels and dimensions
we can get you can achieve coherence
or not and then and the the
sociopath dynamic
has an incoherent in it almost by
definition
by by definition right okay
so this this then plugs into an aspect
of cars
and it also picks up on whitehead so
this idea that
these kinds of these kinds of antichrist
perversions wow
i wouldn't notice uttering this sentence
right
whitehead said though the one saving
grace we always have is that evil is
ultimately self-destructive
that there's that right that yes right
right because it's engaged because it's
ultimately doing stuff that's reciprocal
narrowing
and incoherent it ultimately is
self-destructive and this is why you see
like but so let's do the prussian state
you know the depression state
um it's going to have difficulty long
terms um
and what you see is initially those
states take off uh think of world war ii
uh germany takes off
right but the nazi state
precisely lacks a capacity for
self-correction
it right it has no capacity for
continuity and the democracies actually
eventually overtake
now there's also all kinds of other but
the capacity for self-correction
where where what's going on there then
if i understand it and this is a dewian
perspective is that
what what the the
i don't know what to call it uh that
there is
or maybe it keeps his idea of an ideal
there is we're looking for people who
have
a component of wisdom enhanced relevance
realization
that can discern when
they are they are involved in a process
that has the self-correcting capacity to
maintain a continuity of development
is that is that is that capturing it
well that's
that's that's working for me and i'll
actually let me let me track it into the
uh updated tripartite model of
consciousness you know
so i'd say experiential phenomenological
coming out of the whole brain
and the the layer there is the
attentional filter okay where's the
witnessing function pulling whole brain
and on top of that you have a narrator
that's narrating the witnessing function
what it's seen and creating a
justification narrative
of identity then you have a public self
that is now saying i'm going to justify
what it is that i'm doing in relation
yeah right you call those what the
intentional filter the freighting filter
the ligerian filter
bingo exactly right and so that's where
the disco here d coherence is going to
be
right somewhere in there there is an
attentional system that's hiding an
episodic memory
a justified intent another an othering
of what the actual game is that's being
played
and through the attentional filter the
freudian filter rogerian filter there is
not authenticity so we're tracking the
filters through the interface between
phenomenology narration and public
justification so this is then this is
the platformic argument no which is a
compliment to you greg it's not it's not
meant to be
the idea that um outer justice right
with it within the commons has to be
completely
anagogically resonant with sophists and
inner justice
absolutely right you need the vertical
horizontal coherence or else you're not
going to
right so but i'm i'm what i'm doing then
is i'm at my
head again move and try to make i we've
got we've talked about the vertical
we've talked about the horizontal
but there but there's also i mean the
horizontal isn't the same thing as the
developmental
right okay right right right it's across
the
the time dimension right level
development okay the time dimension when
it's developmental i mean the horizontal
time in one state i'm trying to get it
i'm trying to propose it as a
developmental accident
right i'm i'm on it i'm on it so i want
to
go ahead and i just i want to quickly
just invoke the cue continuum just fyi
that's my modification of the three cues
um in in the sense that continuity if
it's continuity is continuity with the
whole
so we were just kind of looking at it
from the lens of continuity more or less
in sort of the sense of self
okay and itself in relationship and then
we did like objective
but that notion of like the polynesian
continuity
continuity is continuity right once you
begin to hit on that and you can
hold that and recognize that once you're
out of integrity you're out of integrity
with the whole universe
all right that's good that is good the
flow with nature that's
at the center of taoism and at the
center of stoicis
all right being able to and all the
great wisdom traditions right really
they
they do they plug you in they transcend
the ego and then all of a sudden you're
in a non-dual oneness
so we should we should open up the
metaphor then you know i'm an ecology
of functions that needs an ecology of
practices
that will put me into the ecology of
nature i mean that's
that's basically what needs to happen
yes
that's right all right that's right
which is atonement
yes yes coming back home
in which the antichrist fakes and we
have to have to find that
and then you know boom and and have
the walls of the civilian is about
bringing you know the good faith flow
into death that's right that's exactly
right
and then and and the bounty is in fact
the recognition that we live in a moment
where within the context of the walls of
the civilian
and held by the fellowship the
possibility of abundance is made real
yes absolutely yes and if we do it
developmentally from a you know to go
back to the early phases of childhood if
we start resonating early in the
attachment structure
and we do that healthy with a with the
educational developmental structure
then the opportunity to grow people
ready through and through
much more present right because then
you're not corrupted
but then we need to change the
educational system and this is zack
stein's argument i think
i think but this goes back to what i
said we have to move
out of a model of
person that is exhausted by the notions
of consumer and citizens
we have to get what is we have to
we have to enrich the model of
personhood it is good and fine and right
that we are talking about all the
process
but right we people people have to have
like they have to have a model of
personhood that enables and affords and
legitimates that process
right so that i came across uh this guy
peter osorio developed thing called
descriptive psychology i didn't know
anything about it but it's this little
sort of and and crucial to him is what
is a person all right and
essentially what he articulates very
different than a human being
a person is what a human being learns to
become yeah okay
right um and what he said is it's i'll
put it slightly in my language
it's the capacity to justify yourself in
a social stage and take account
and responsibility for your actions
that's essentially what it is that a
person is
okay um so then we put that in and our
fundamental responsibility
is the good faith participation in
the commons in the in the harmonizing
of the structure then now you have
justifiable accountability
now that that the person then to become
clean in relationship to that
will become a concept that plugs in i
believe to that
structure yeah just you know again i
want to kind of
communicate back out to anybody who's
observing
that one of the very powerful insights
that i think
this that simplifies but reduces the
weight
is is to say look how okay how are we
gonna do this
and you know there's like two immediate
flags
this is absolutely not in the least bit
utopian
um and it's also not particularly
idealistic
right what i'm going to say is this
there's going to be a lot of practical
questions
how do we do these kinds of things in
very specific cases
and in almost every one of those cases
my answer is i don't know
but i i've noticed just in this
conversation that greg's got some pretty
cool
and john's got some pretty cool and
as long as we're all operating with
those three
basics we're operating with a very
strong orientation towards personal
integrity
interpersonal dignity and a collective
orientation towards the access monday
of the uh of the well-being of each and
all
are mutually combined then i get the
benefit of craig's cool
and so i can start saying okay well i
don't need to know it's not my job to
know the things i don't know it's my job
to know the things i know
to be very strong in those and skillful
and bring them with
generosity into the collective endeavor
and then to
be able to find the network the comments
right the networks
the comments combine those two words
together right you find those who have
the peace and then empower them to bring
their peace into the whole
it doesn't take that long all right a
little bit of getting that right you can
start getting that
have this visual this visual image of uh
of like uh
when the when the water comes in from
the beach into from the ocean to the
beach and it kind of fills up a low
point
and there's just a tiny trickle of water
flowing back to the ocean
but it but every movement of the water
takes a piece of sand
away so it gets lower so it accelerates
and you certainly have the whole thing
come back
like that's what it's going to look like
how's that that's the dynamic
i like that especially
the synthesis of networking and comments
yes that's so crucial very very well
said
that's very well said so i think you
said it first
in this conversation and probably
michelle balance has been saying it for
15 years from
thailand okay well
this feels like a good place to end for
today
all right so i want to we rode the wave
yeah yeah yeah i think this is very very
good
and i think we made some
good socratic process the progress and
through the process
um so first of all i want to thank my my
my good friends
uh greg enriquez and jordan hall um
and i would my pleasure i would like to
invite both of them for us to do another
one of these
at some point because i think this is
beneficial to
everybody who's coming into i mean into
this problematic
of uh how should we live well now
but also how should we live well now for
the future um and so
um again thank you guys very much very
much appreciate it
yeah amen very cool very cool
all right guys bye-bye all right great